<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Comments | APARAJITH RAGHUVIR</title>
    <link>https://aparajith21.github.io/tags/comments/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://aparajith21.github.io/tags/comments/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Comments</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© Aparajith Raghuvir 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://aparajith21.github.io/media/aparajith.jpg</url>
      <title>Comments</title>
      <link>https://aparajith21.github.io/tags/comments/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>New years and Resolutions</title>
      <link>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/new-years-and-resolutions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/new-years-and-resolutions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So 2020 is finally over and it’s the start of a new year. Many of us make a resolution at the beginning of the year, but &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.westernconnecticuthealthnetwork.org/newsroom/article-listing/new-years-resolutions&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;fewer than 10% keep it for more than a few months&lt;/a&gt;. Personally, I don’t believe in the concept of resolutions - they’re nugatory and pointless in my opinion- yet I will attempt one this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, when I was younger, I used to be a voracious reader and read far too many books, some of which were too advanced for my age. But to my shock, I’ve completely lost the habit of reading books - to the best of memory, I read exactly one book last year (Vishy Anand’s autobiographical ‘Mind Master’). I wouldn’t say I have lost the habit of &lt;em&gt;reading&lt;/em&gt; - I did read a lot of academic papers last year, but they do not lend themselves for casual discussion with friends and family- I’ve just lost the habit of reading &lt;em&gt;books&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to rectify that this year, and hence I make a resolution to read 52 books this year, one every week. I’m going to read books that I haven’t read before and also re-read some books, both non-fiction (to see how I interpret them with my more mature outlook) and fiction (for entertainment). I confess that when I was younger, the distribution of books I read would be 80-20 in favour of fiction against non-fiction. I hope to change that as well and bring down the disparity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I’m not going to force my progression to be linear - some books deserve more time than others and some weeks I may not feel like reading a book- and expect myself to read exactly one book a week. Such an expectation would be the downfall of this resolution as it would cause unnecessary anxiety and even make reading books a  &lt;em&gt;chore&lt;/em&gt; or something to be ticked off a list instead of provoking thought and providing entertainment and recreation (I believe a major reason for the collapse of resolutions is the anxiety it causes and the way it makes a task chore-like). Nor am I going to be a pedant and consider it a failure if I don’t read 52 books. I will be satisfied if I return to the habit of reading books this year and keep to the &lt;em&gt;spirit&lt;/em&gt; of the resolution, regardless of the number of books I read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am posting this on the internet so that it offers me some motivation and negative reinforcement. I don’t want someone reading this (if at all anyone visits this website), and showing a screenshot later next year of how I did not keep to my resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will update the following list of books I&amp;rsquo;ve read this year as and when I finish one. I shall not be keeping count - that will be left for the pedants out there. Wish me luck for I will need it to be among the 10%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Made_in_Japan_%28biography%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Made in Japan : Akio Morita and Sony&lt;/a&gt; (autobiography of Akio Morita) - Sunday, 03/01/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Black_Swan:_The_Impact_of_the_Highly_Improbable&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Black Swan: The Impact of the Highly Improbable&lt;/a&gt; by Nassim Nicholas Taleb - Thursday, 14/01/21&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.co.in/books/about/My_Life_in_Red_and_White.html?id=IMmDzQEACAAJ&amp;amp;source=kp_book_description&amp;amp;redir_esc=y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;My Life in Red and White&lt;/a&gt; by Arsene Wenger (autobiography) - Monday, 18/01/21&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/54494984-the-commonwealth-of-cricket&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Commonwealth of Cricket: A Lifelong Love Affair with the Most Subtle and Sophisticated Game Known to Humankind&lt;/a&gt; by Ramachandra Guha - Wednesday 27/01/21&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Future_Shock&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Future Shock&lt;/a&gt; by Alvin Toffler - Wednesday 31/03/21&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>US Elections 2020: A battle for conscience</title>
      <link>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/us-elections-2020-a-battle-for-conscience/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/us-elections-2020-a-battle-for-conscience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m no expert on US politics, but I&amp;rsquo;m anyway sharing my thoughts here on this election in the world’s oldest democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before this unprecedented pandemic, unemployment rates had fallen, consumer confidence was rising, home sales were also on the rise and the stock market in the US was booming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, all of that has since changed this year thanks to the coronavirus.
Most people would agree that the US President hasn’t handled the pandemic well in terms of loss of life and damage to health, but the economy in the US isn’t too worse off either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why is the US so bitterly divided with no clear result yet?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if Mr Biden does end up becoming the next President, it doesn’t take anything away from the fact that almost half of the US has voted for Mr Trump! It will be a political victory for Mr Biden but not a victory for equity and fairness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you’re willing to chalk off Mr Trump’s handling of this pandemic given its unprecedented nature, he’s done well in terms of the economy, with jobs created and people occupied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s pretty much all you can give to the President.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Socially, the US is more divided than ever, with a President who turns the other way when minorities are targeted, who doesn’t even pretend to care about a large portion of his nation boiling over in anger. He’s treated the situation with complete apathy and disregard resulting in massive polarisation of the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who did vote for Mr Trump can be classified into two types: those unaffected by the systemic racism and targeting of minorities, and two, those that are indeed concerned but lacking the conscience to look beyond the ‘good’ handling of the economy, and engulfed by a twisted sense of &amp;lsquo;patriotism&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make no mistake, those who are affected probably voted for Mr Biden. But what about those who did vote for Mr. Trump, and that is almost half of all voters?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forget the Trump &amp;lsquo;bhakts&amp;rsquo;. It is the rest, who were indeed aware of Mr Trump&amp;rsquo;s true colours but still chose to vote for him without a touch of conscience or morality, that we should be concerned about.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
