<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Science | APARAJITH RAGHUVIR</title>
    <link>https://aparajith21.github.io/tags/science/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://aparajith21.github.io/tags/science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Science</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© Aparajith Raghuvir 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://aparajith21.github.io/media/aparajith.jpg</url>
      <title>Science</title>
      <link>https://aparajith21.github.io/tags/science/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Significance of the discovery of Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/significance-of-the-discovery-of-gravitational-waves/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/significance-of-the-discovery-of-gravitational-waves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been a bit of a hiatus for me. The extremely over hyped 10th board exams are coming up next month in March. I strongly believe exams must never have a role in deciding the capabilities of a person. Every person will have a field where they&amp;rsquo;re brilliant, only exams won&amp;rsquo;t identify those people. Extremely smart people might still fail to perform to the best of their abilities during examinations due to various reasons- from pressure to exam fear. One day, when I take humans to Mars, I will make sure that the first thing that is instituted is a proper education system. &lt;em&gt;Sighs and wakes up to realize I&amp;rsquo;m still a nobody and we&amp;rsquo;re still on Earth with my Boards in a month.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now to get to the topic and the purpose of writing this article, which I just could not resist writing being a science fanatic, despite pressures from family, friends and teachers to seriously spend time studying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gravitational waves are basically ripples in the space-time continuum or the fabric of space and time, the existence of which was brilliantly predicted by Albert Einstein almost a century ago(98 years).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mass bends space. In a more simple way, take space to be like a long piece of sponge. If you apply pressure on the sponge, it bends due to mass of your hand right? The harder you press, the more it bends. Similarly, due to the gravitational forces of various bodies, space gets &amp;lsquo;bent&amp;rsquo; and disturbed from its original position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gravity doesn&amp;rsquo;t act as a force, in fact there are no &amp;lsquo;forces&amp;rsquo; in the gravitational pull, it is actually because due to the mass of both the objects, space bends due to which the objects move closer to each other. Now, imagine two ends of a paper sheet. Mark an edge as &amp;lsquo;A&amp;rsquo; and it&amp;rsquo;s opposite side as &amp;lsquo;B&amp;rsquo;. Now to go from an edge to the other, you need to go via the diagonal right? Now, what happens if you fold the sheet via the other diagonal. This reduces the distance and now A is literally on B right? This is exactly what happens when celestial bodies attract each other due to a bend in space time caused by the mass of their bodies(gravity), only there is more space between them unlike when A is on top of B(LOL).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ANYTHING with MASS and ENERGY can create gravitational force(even me and you). If you run around, even then you cause ripples in the fabric of space-time, although it will be undetectable and very, very, very small. Now, to cause such a massive distortion, you need something very very big moving very, very fast for us to detect it. This is why gravitational waves were possible to be detected only from 2 massive black holes moving at incredible speeds&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes coming to it now, there is only one way to detect gravitational waves which bend space and time. Take a guess. And before taking one, let me give you the facts. Say you want to measure the distance between A and B which is originally 10 cm. Even if you make markings equally spaced between each other, you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to notice and detect any change, as a bend in the space-time continuum say which causes A and B to come closer will also cause the markings to come closer, so you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to identify any difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only thing which doesn&amp;rsquo;t get stretched is light(the speed). Say due to the disturbances, the distance between A and B gets stretched further, then light will take more speed to reach B and if it gets bent and becomes smaller, then light will take lesser time to reach B. This is exactly how they detected the existence of gravitational waves at LIGO(Laser Interferometer Gravitational Wave Observatory). There are 2 tunnels there, perpendicular to each other, When a gravitational wave is detected, one of the tunnels stretches while the other contracts. The interference of the lasers as the waves bounce between the different points in the vertex is measured to check whether space-time has been bent or not. It is super mega ultra giga difficult to do this and successfully measure the differences. Like say measuring a difference of 50 cm from the original size of a rod which is 100,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,00 m long. I bet you can&amp;rsquo;t even read the number correctly! Adding to the difficulties is the extra noise which heightens the difficulty of successfully detecting a gravitational wave. This is done by comparing the ripples gotten in experiments to the ones in actual space-time ripples. It&amp;rsquo;s like a 10000 different songs being played at the same time and you&amp;rsquo;re trying to identify a melody whose volume is the lowest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The significance of this achievement is well, SIGNIFICANT as it provides a completely different view and perception of the universe. Until today, gravity was thought of as a normal force. But now, it has been clearly proven that space and time can be bent. You can now look at things from a totally different angle. Like say, you initially were only able to see 2 dimensions, but now you&amp;rsquo;re able to see the 3rd and this completely changes your understanding of the world, nothing is flat anymore. It is absolutely incredible how a man who lived almost a century ago, was able to see with such foresight and predict such an &amp;lsquo;absurd&amp;rsquo; thing as this. Maybe he was born in a future world and he traveled back in time and unfortunately lost his time machine and enlightened the world earlier than when it was supposed to understand various stuffs. If he did that, the consequences would possibly only be known to him and could affect the world adversely. Oh hell, only the worst critic of Einstein would put forth such a theory and somehow manage to criticize him. For all we know, Einstein was a great man, a fabulous human being who has made the world a more knowledgeable one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now that it has been proven that space time is like a sheet which can be bent, I just can&amp;rsquo;t wait for the sheet to become 3 dimensional! That&amp;rsquo;ll deepen further our understanding of the research able
universe.
This is one great step in the quest for knowledge and understanding of the universe and the physics behind it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: This article was first published in my retired &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reasonwhyy.blogspot.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; on 12 February 2016. This is a copy of it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dreams</title>
      <link>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/dreams/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/dreams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We dream about 2-6 times almost every night(or day), but we never wonder what they actually are and most of the time, you forget what you dreamt of when you wake up and even sometimes when you remember, you just put it aside and focus on more worldy thoughts. None of us realize though, that our  brains can think the clearest and deepest while we&amp;rsquo;re dreaming. So here&amp;rsquo;s how I understand dreaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would define a dream as ideas, emotions and thoughts that converge to form a sort of a movie in your head which you sometimes can, but sometimes can&amp;rsquo;t control. Although I&amp;rsquo;m no oneirologist or a psychoanalyst, this is my view about dreams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, dreams usually materialize based on my last thought before falling asleep. So, therefore before going to bed, I think about stuff which I like and stuff which I wonder a lot about, like Chelsea winning, rebelling against your genetic composition etc, and sometimes when I&amp;rsquo;m in my dream I command the world and can therefore try different scenarios to put to bed my curiosities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While you&amp;rsquo;re fully conscious, there are stuff which are highly impossible to successfully recreate in the conscious world. In a dream, even the sky is not the limit. You can achieve ANYTHING in a dream. The world belongs to you. All you need to do is know how to control it. They can help you get creative and give a sense of inspiration and ideas. You can actually solve problems better in your dreams than in a conscious state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dreams can also be re-visualizations of good or scary moments of the past which affect you emotionally, either causing anxieties and fears or happiness and nostalgia. You dream about happy moments of the past which you wish to relive or about repressed memories and phobias during which you fathom about what would happen if such a thing were to occur in real life. You go through different possibilities, of how you could&amp;rsquo;ve made a good moment better, or of how you&amp;rsquo;d react were to be placed in an unpleasant situation which you fear while conscious. You get ideas on how to tackle such situations and to beat your fears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, in rare cases, you will come to understand that you&amp;rsquo;re dreaming. How you do varies from person to person. Like for me, during rare instances when I suspect that I&amp;rsquo;m dreaming, a door with a sunflower on it suddenly appears which makes realization dawn on me. I have absolutely no idea why it&amp;rsquo;s a sunflower door nor can I change it. It has been the same from when I was young and is probably because of my experiences then. If I choose to stay, I can sort of influence the events in the world of dreams, but I also wake up if I open the door and walk through it. I have no idea why this is so and find it incredibly bizarre. This is basically known as lucid dreaming. You are aware that you&amp;rsquo;re dreaming and sometimes, can even control and influence the events occurring in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dreams consolidate newer memories and reinforce older ones combining them with your thoughts to provide you a better view and ideas to sate your curiosities and abate your deepest desires which widely vary from person to person. They help in enlightening you and broadening your view on subjects. They also serve as reminders for things which you should do in the future or bring back visions of people who were in your life in the past who you dearly miss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, they also serve as warnings for future occurrences which may probably take place due to a series of events culminating into one big showdown. Sometimes, people get premonitions or visions about future events that are going to take place. Many put forth a religious and spiritual point of view to these &amp;lsquo;premonitions&amp;rsquo; like astrology, divination, necromancy etc but this is my view on this. Some people have a very good IQ(Intelligence Quotient). Usually, these are the ones who get these visions about the future in their dreams. I would say this is because their mind is sharp enough to analyse certain small and seemingly insignificant events, but all of which might have possible consequences. There are people who have &amp;lsquo;predicted&amp;rsquo; future disasters and are being called &amp;lsquo;Oracles&amp;rsquo; or so but they are probably those whose minds are intelligent enough to put together a few factors which might cause a disaster in which man might have had a role to play. Like say, in EM Forster&amp;rsquo;s, the Machine Stops, although he wrote it as science fiction, he was able to successfully predict a world which is highly dependent on machines and the Internet and instant messaging services back in 1909. He had such good foresight, that it almost seems as if he travelled through time and wrote the book back in 1909. These kinds of people have incredible IQs and could possibly be able to put together events which may culminate with them predicting the final event in the future subconsciously. They are basically the ones we revere and call Oracles. At least, that is my opinion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most difficult part I face is that about 90% of the time, when I realize that I&amp;rsquo;m dreaming, I wake up and am unable to continue the dream. It is very difficult to maintain a subconscious state once you realize that what you&amp;rsquo;re experiencing isn&amp;rsquo;t real and has no effect on you. But after a while, sometimes you master it, and for sometime you control the world of dreams where the Laws of Physics don&amp;rsquo;t apply and you can try out different things which you&amp;rsquo;d have always wanted to do in real life. You can also gain answers to questions and be inspired by the happenings of a dream. But, sometimes, instead of being affected by the outside environment and waking up, the brain incorporates this as a part of the dream resulting in continued sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The toughest part though is to recall and remember a dream, and even when you do it is extremely unreliable as most of the time, you mix reality with the dreamscape and get an altered version of the dream. But, that said, if you awake while in the middle of the dream, you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to fully recall and remember it, but what use is it when you wake up while in the middle of solving something. Mostly, you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to recall dreams which are vivid and interesting in content making you curious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah, this is my interpretation of dreams. If your dreams don&amp;rsquo;t scare you, they aren&amp;rsquo;t big enough, so dream big!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: Not taking anything away from EM Forster for he was one of the best science fiction writers in the world. Plus, this is just my view of a dream, you may not agree with this, but this is what I believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: This article was first published in my retired &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reasonwhyy.blogspot.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; on 17 November 2015. This is a copy of it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hyperloop</title>
      <link>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/hyperloop/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/hyperloop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-hyperloop&#34;&gt;What is the Hyperloop?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hyperloop is a revolutionary concept put forth by the real world Ironman, Elon Musk. It will revolutionize transportation and is possibly the next big mode of transportation before warping(soon to be invented).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will operate by sending &amp;lsquo;capsules&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;pods&amp;rsquo; into a steel tube which is maintained at a partial vacuum.&lt;br&gt;
Each pod floats on a small pocket of air under pressure. Magnetic Levitation(usage of magnets to create lift, thus attaining great speeds as the vehicle isn&amp;rsquo;t in contact with the ground) is mostly avoided here, yet it goes at speeds which a wheel can&amp;rsquo;t sustain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linear induction motors are used for acceleration and deceleration of the pod. Linear induction motors are basically ones which have the rotor and stator &amp;lsquo;unrotatory&amp;rsquo; so that instead of producing a torque as in traditional motors, a linear force is produced along its length. Similar to regenerative braking, linear motors too store its power when shifting speeds for future use. This is useful during parts of the journey when the speed is greatly increased or decreased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to no tyres, there&amp;rsquo;ll be highly reduced rolling resistance, and the air resistance too will be reduced. This is what enables to pod to float or glide throughout the journey at great speeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in a tube which isn&amp;rsquo;t a total vacuum, there&amp;rsquo;s a problem in which the pod slows down due to pressure building up in front of it.  This is solved by placing an electric inlet fan and an air compressor to move highly pressurised air to the back of the pod. The pods will be solar powered and the maximum acceleration will be 0.5g with an average speed of 750 mph. This is basically the proposed model of the Hyperloop in short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2015-11-17-hyperloop/featured_explanation.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;how it works&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-is-it-going-to-affect-us&#34;&gt;How is it going to affect us?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes us 30 hours on Indian roads to travel from Kanyakumari to Kashmir and we spend so much on petrol and fuel. Imagine a travel time of 2 hours approximately at a cost of ₹1000. Even if air travel was possible, it would take us 3-4 hours to travel that distance plus even the cheapest flight fare would at least cost ₹20000, which is 20 times the cost of  travelling by the Hyperloop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2015-11-17-hyperloop/hyperloop.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;HYPERLOOP TECHNOLOGIES INC.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also weather proof. No matter the conditions, storm, sun or blizzard, this will function. People may say that this is just another similar version of maglev trains, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the big disadvantages that accompany maglev trains ie the huge costs, poor fuel efficiency as levitating requires quite some energy plus the safety is always in question. These are negated in the Hyperloop.
Plus even though, magnetic levitation is put to use here although not to the maglev train level extent, it&amp;rsquo;s energy efficient and utilises solar power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hyperloop basically offers quick transportation and an ecofriendly, weather proof means of transport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: This article was first published in my retired &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reasonwhyy.blogspot.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; on 17 November 2015. This is a copy of it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
