<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Casual | APARAJITH RAGHUVIR</title>
    <link>https://aparajith21.github.io/tags/casual/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://aparajith21.github.io/tags/casual/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Casual</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© Aparajith Raghuvir 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://aparajith21.github.io/media/aparajith.jpg</url>
      <title>Casual</title>
      <link>https://aparajith21.github.io/tags/casual/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>New years and Resolutions</title>
      <link>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/new-years-and-resolutions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/new-years-and-resolutions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So 2020 is finally over and it’s the start of a new year. Many of us make a resolution at the beginning of the year, but &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.westernconnecticuthealthnetwork.org/newsroom/article-listing/new-years-resolutions&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;fewer than 10% keep it for more than a few months&lt;/a&gt;. Personally, I don’t believe in the concept of resolutions - they’re nugatory and pointless in my opinion- yet I will attempt one this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, when I was younger, I used to be a voracious reader and read far too many books, some of which were too advanced for my age. But to my shock, I’ve completely lost the habit of reading books - to the best of memory, I read exactly one book last year (Vishy Anand’s autobiographical ‘Mind Master’). I wouldn’t say I have lost the habit of &lt;em&gt;reading&lt;/em&gt; - I did read a lot of academic papers last year, but they do not lend themselves for casual discussion with friends and family- I’ve just lost the habit of reading &lt;em&gt;books&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to rectify that this year, and hence I make a resolution to read 52 books this year, one every week. I’m going to read books that I haven’t read before and also re-read some books, both non-fiction (to see how I interpret them with my more mature outlook) and fiction (for entertainment). I confess that when I was younger, the distribution of books I read would be 80-20 in favour of fiction against non-fiction. I hope to change that as well and bring down the disparity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I’m not going to force my progression to be linear - some books deserve more time than others and some weeks I may not feel like reading a book- and expect myself to read exactly one book a week. Such an expectation would be the downfall of this resolution as it would cause unnecessary anxiety and even make reading books a  &lt;em&gt;chore&lt;/em&gt; or something to be ticked off a list instead of provoking thought and providing entertainment and recreation (I believe a major reason for the collapse of resolutions is the anxiety it causes and the way it makes a task chore-like). Nor am I going to be a pedant and consider it a failure if I don’t read 52 books. I will be satisfied if I return to the habit of reading books this year and keep to the &lt;em&gt;spirit&lt;/em&gt; of the resolution, regardless of the number of books I read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am posting this on the internet so that it offers me some motivation and negative reinforcement. I don’t want someone reading this (if at all anyone visits this website), and showing a screenshot later next year of how I did not keep to my resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will update the following list of books I&amp;rsquo;ve read this year as and when I finish one. I shall not be keeping count - that will be left for the pedants out there. Wish me luck for I will need it to be among the 10%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Made_in_Japan_%28biography%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Made in Japan : Akio Morita and Sony&lt;/a&gt; (autobiography of Akio Morita) - Sunday, 03/01/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Black_Swan:_The_Impact_of_the_Highly_Improbable&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Black Swan: The Impact of the Highly Improbable&lt;/a&gt; by Nassim Nicholas Taleb - Thursday, 14/01/21&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.co.in/books/about/My_Life_in_Red_and_White.html?id=IMmDzQEACAAJ&amp;amp;source=kp_book_description&amp;amp;redir_esc=y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;My Life in Red and White&lt;/a&gt; by Arsene Wenger (autobiography) - Monday, 18/01/21&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/54494984-the-commonwealth-of-cricket&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Commonwealth of Cricket: A Lifelong Love Affair with the Most Subtle and Sophisticated Game Known to Humankind&lt;/a&gt; by Ramachandra Guha - Wednesday 27/01/21&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Future_Shock&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Future Shock&lt;/a&gt; by Alvin Toffler - Wednesday 31/03/21&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kane_and_Abel_%28novel%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kane and Abel&lt;/a&gt; by Jeffrey Archer - Saturday 05/06/21&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Osterman_Weekend&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Osterman Weekend&lt;/a&gt; by Robert Ludlum - Monday 08/06/21&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tosses and the IPL</title>
      <link>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/tosses-and-the-ipl/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/tosses-and-the-ipl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The toss of a coin signifies the start of every cricket match. The winning captain gets to decide whether his team bats or bowls first. Generally, right from grassroots cricket, the idea that is taught by coaches is to win the toss, bat first, put up a good total and then defend it. And this is still relevant in test match cricket and is what usually happens, unless there’re absurdly windy conditions or conditions favourable to bowling, teams win the toss and bat first stating the reason that the pitch will likely erode over five days making it difficult for the team that bats last&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, it’s slightly different in limited overs cricket, where in cases of day night matches, teams take into consideration factors like dew, that might make it more difficult for the team that bowls second. But even here, it’s mostly bat first, especially in pressure-situations even if there is the likelihood of dew, like how Sri Lanka did against India in the 2011 world cup final in dewy conditions at the Wankhede stadium in Mumbai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in T20 cricket, this logic has inverted itself, especially in recent times. In the IPL, between 2008 and 2012 (inclusive of both), when T20 cricket was slowly maturing from the infant it was in 2008 to the toddler in 2012, teams which won the toss chose to bat and field first roughly half the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, the tide has changed rapidly. Toss winning teams nowadays prefer to field first and chase down a target that they know. Between 2013 and 2016 (inclusive of both), teams that won the toss chose to field first 61% of the time, a significant increase from the 50% in the preceding five seasons. Teams batted first only if they were sure that the pitch would deteriorate significantly through the match. Teams that won the toss and bowled first won the game 54% of the time and teams that won the toss and batted first won only 43% of the time. Make of that what you will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been another massive shift since 2016. T20 cricket has grown up some more and between 2017 and 2019 (inclusive of both), teams that won the toss chose to field first an incredible 83% of the time! This decision lead the toss winning team to victory 58% of the time whereas teams that won the toss and chose to bat first were able to justify their decision 51% of the time, over the 43% in the previous 4 years. So teams that chose to bat first were somewhat smarter with their decision compared to earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The IPLs between 2017 and 2019 were all held in India, and the current one is happening in the UAE. Here too teams have chosen to field first in most of the initial games, though the trend is changing now though, with Kolkata Knight Riders choosing to bat first against CSK (toss occurred at the time of writing) in the 33rd time of asking since they last batted first in 2015! Maybe it’s because there’s hardly any dew present to mitigate the general slowdown of the pitch that teams are going back to batting first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is the reason for this field first craze? Results are not too skewed in the favour of the team that chooses to field first (58-42) to justify this. There could be many reasons, if I am to guess, it is probably due to the pitches being relatively easy to bat on throughout and it’s simply easier to chase a target than to set one, plus the dew factor..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In IPL finals though, 7 out of 12 times, the team winning the toss chose to bat first, and weirdly, both the toss winning teams in the first 2 seasons of the IPL fielded first (1 W, 1 L). Of the 4 latest finals though, the team winning the toss has won each of the finals and in 3 of the 4 finals, the toss winning team chose to bat first, interestingly, in contrast to how toss winning teams generally chose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting factoid is that of the 4 finals Mumbai and Chennai have contested, the team that batted first won every time, and in 3 of those finals, the team winning the toss chose to bat first. Mumbai have also won every final in which they batted first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, it is upto the cricket experts to shine light on these trends and the decision making of the toss winning teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you read this, do ping me with your opinion on this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data was obtained from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/nowke9/ipldata&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;kaggle&lt;/a&gt; under the Creative Commons license.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arunachal Photo Diary</title>
      <link>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/arunachal-photo-diary/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/arunachal-photo-diary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We started from Chennai on the 22nd of December, flying to Dibrugarh via Kolkata. We reached Dibrugarh at 2 p.m. and were anxious to get out of that place due to the ensuing protests against the CAA. We entered Arunachal at around 4 and reached the Golden Pagoda at Namsai at around 1730 in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/map.png&#34; alt=&#34;Map of Arunachal Pradesh&#34;&gt;
Route Taken: Namsai (Namsai District) (Day 1) -&amp;gt; Hawai (Anjaw District) (Day 2) -&amp;gt; Dong (Day 3) -&amp;gt; Kibithu (Day 4) -&amp;gt; Tezu (Lohit District) (Day 5) -&amp;gt; Roing (Lower Dibang Valley District) (Day 6) -&amp;gt; Pasighat (East Siang District) (Day 6)-&amp;gt; Dibrugarh (Day 8) -&amp;gt; Chennai&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/IMG_20200115_133044.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Golden Pagoda, Namsai&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Golden Pagoda, Namsai&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/golden_buddha.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Golden Buddha&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Golden Buddha&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/morning_golden_pagoda.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Golden Pagoda in the morning&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Golden Pagoda in the morning&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/IMG_20200115_133214.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tengapani River from eco resort&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;View of the Tengapani river from the eco-resort at Namsai&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/tengapani.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tengapani River&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Tengapani River&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/IMG_20200115_133322.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Monastery by the Tengapani River&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Monastery by the Tengapani River&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/parashuram_kund.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Parashuram Kund by the Lohit River&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Parashuram Kund by Lohit River&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/BRO.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Interesting from the BRO&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Interesting board from the BRO&lt;/figcaption&gt;
Other more interesting boards on the road by the BRO include:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you drive like hell, soon you will be there&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better be Mr Late than late Mr&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Safety on the road is safe tea at home&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After whiskey, driving risky&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your hurry may cause your family worry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is not a race, drive with grace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep your nerves on sharp curves; &amp;amp; many others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/lohit_dong.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lohit River at Dong&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Lohit River at Dong, near Walong&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/hanging_bridge1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;First hanging bridge&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;First and safest looking hanging bridge of the trip&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/IMG_20200115_133555.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;View from hanging bridge&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;View from the hanging bridge&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/view_bridge2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;View from the hanging bridge&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;View from the hanging bridge&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/bridge_view3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;View from the 2nd hanging bridge of the trip&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;View from the 2nd hanging bridge of the trip&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/view_bridge4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;View from 2nd hanging bridge&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;View from the 2nd hanging bridge of the trip&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/war_memorial.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;War Memorial near Walong&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;War Memorial near Walong&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/eastern.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Easternmost Outposts of the Indian Army&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Easternmost Outposts of the Indian Army&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/bunker.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Army bunker&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Army bunker at Kibithu&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/bestpic.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;View on the road to Kibithu from Walong&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;figcaptionview-on-the-road-to-kibithu-from-walongfigcaption&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;View on the road to Kibithu from Walong&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/indochinborder.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Indo-China border (Madan Ridge),  perpendicular to it is the border with Burma&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Indo-China border (Maden Ridge), 
perpendicular to it is the border with Burma&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/springs.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Hot springs at Walong&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Hot springs at Walong&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/dong_resort.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dong Resort at Walong&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Dong Resort at Walong&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/memorial1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;War memorial at Walong&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;War memorial at Walong&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/memorial2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;War memorial at Walong&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;War memorial at Walong&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/memorial3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;War memorial at Walong&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;War memorial at Walong&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/memorial4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;War memorial at Walong&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;War memorial at Walong&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/washed_bridge.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Bridge keeps getting washed away in the monsoon&amp;hellip;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Bridge keeps getting washed away in the monsoon...&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/sally.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sally Lake, Roing &#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Sally Lake, Roing &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/siang1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Siang River&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Siang River&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/abor.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Abor Country River Camp&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Abor Country River Camp&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/yamne.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Yamne River&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Yamne River&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/bridge_last_View.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;View from the last hanging bridge of the trip&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;View from the last hanging bridge of the trip&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://aparajith21.github.io/post/2020-02-16-arunachal-photo-diary/broken_bridge.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A broken hanging bridge, right next to the one we&amp;rsquo;re on!&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A broken hanging bridge, right next to the one we&#39;re on!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We went river rafting in Pasighat, and returned to Chennai on the 29th after one of our most memorable holidays, that included adventures like the car getting stuck on the ghat road in the night with rain pouring down and nowhere to go, with nobody on the road, to being forced to stop to wait for a landslide to get cleared !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading (viewing the pictures).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: This article was first published in my retired &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reasonwhyy.blogspot.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; on 16 February 2020. This is a copy of it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Arunachal is one of the most beautiful states in India, and surely more people need to go and appreciate it&amp;rsquo;s beauty when they can in this pandemic.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dreams</title>
      <link>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/dreams/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/dreams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We dream about 2-6 times almost every night(or day), but we never wonder what they actually are and most of the time, you forget what you dreamt of when you wake up and even sometimes when you remember, you just put it aside and focus on more worldy thoughts. None of us realize though, that our  brains can think the clearest and deepest while we&amp;rsquo;re dreaming. So here&amp;rsquo;s how I understand dreaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would define a dream as ideas, emotions and thoughts that converge to form a sort of a movie in your head which you sometimes can, but sometimes can&amp;rsquo;t control. Although I&amp;rsquo;m no oneirologist or a psychoanalyst, this is my view about dreams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, dreams usually materialize based on my last thought before falling asleep. So, therefore before going to bed, I think about stuff which I like and stuff which I wonder a lot about, like Chelsea winning, rebelling against your genetic composition etc, and sometimes when I&amp;rsquo;m in my dream I command the world and can therefore try different scenarios to put to bed my curiosities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While you&amp;rsquo;re fully conscious, there are stuff which are highly impossible to successfully recreate in the conscious world. In a dream, even the sky is not the limit. You can achieve ANYTHING in a dream. The world belongs to you. All you need to do is know how to control it. They can help you get creative and give a sense of inspiration and ideas. You can actually solve problems better in your dreams than in a conscious state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dreams can also be re-visualizations of good or scary moments of the past which affect you emotionally, either causing anxieties and fears or happiness and nostalgia. You dream about happy moments of the past which you wish to relive or about repressed memories and phobias during which you fathom about what would happen if such a thing were to occur in real life. You go through different possibilities, of how you could&amp;rsquo;ve made a good moment better, or of how you&amp;rsquo;d react were to be placed in an unpleasant situation which you fear while conscious. You get ideas on how to tackle such situations and to beat your fears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, in rare cases, you will come to understand that you&amp;rsquo;re dreaming. How you do varies from person to person. Like for me, during rare instances when I suspect that I&amp;rsquo;m dreaming, a door with a sunflower on it suddenly appears which makes realization dawn on me. I have absolutely no idea why it&amp;rsquo;s a sunflower door nor can I change it. It has been the same from when I was young and is probably because of my experiences then. If I choose to stay, I can sort of influence the events in the world of dreams, but I also wake up if I open the door and walk through it. I have no idea why this is so and find it incredibly bizarre. This is basically known as lucid dreaming. You are aware that you&amp;rsquo;re dreaming and sometimes, can even control and influence the events occurring in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dreams consolidate newer memories and reinforce older ones combining them with your thoughts to provide you a better view and ideas to sate your curiosities and abate your deepest desires which widely vary from person to person. They help in enlightening you and broadening your view on subjects. They also serve as reminders for things which you should do in the future or bring back visions of people who were in your life in the past who you dearly miss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, they also serve as warnings for future occurrences which may probably take place due to a series of events culminating into one big showdown. Sometimes, people get premonitions or visions about future events that are going to take place. Many put forth a religious and spiritual point of view to these &amp;lsquo;premonitions&amp;rsquo; like astrology, divination, necromancy etc but this is my view on this. Some people have a very good IQ(Intelligence Quotient). Usually, these are the ones who get these visions about the future in their dreams. I would say this is because their mind is sharp enough to analyse certain small and seemingly insignificant events, but all of which might have possible consequences. There are people who have &amp;lsquo;predicted&amp;rsquo; future disasters and are being called &amp;lsquo;Oracles&amp;rsquo; or so but they are probably those whose minds are intelligent enough to put together a few factors which might cause a disaster in which man might have had a role to play. Like say, in EM Forster&amp;rsquo;s, the Machine Stops, although he wrote it as science fiction, he was able to successfully predict a world which is highly dependent on machines and the Internet and instant messaging services back in 1909. He had such good foresight, that it almost seems as if he travelled through time and wrote the book back in 1909. These kinds of people have incredible IQs and could possibly be able to put together events which may culminate with them predicting the final event in the future subconsciously. They are basically the ones we revere and call Oracles. At least, that is my opinion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most difficult part I face is that about 90% of the time, when I realize that I&amp;rsquo;m dreaming, I wake up and am unable to continue the dream. It is very difficult to maintain a subconscious state once you realize that what you&amp;rsquo;re experiencing isn&amp;rsquo;t real and has no effect on you. But after a while, sometimes you master it, and for sometime you control the world of dreams where the Laws of Physics don&amp;rsquo;t apply and you can try out different things which you&amp;rsquo;d have always wanted to do in real life. You can also gain answers to questions and be inspired by the happenings of a dream. But, sometimes, instead of being affected by the outside environment and waking up, the brain incorporates this as a part of the dream resulting in continued sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The toughest part though is to recall and remember a dream, and even when you do it is extremely unreliable as most of the time, you mix reality with the dreamscape and get an altered version of the dream. But, that said, if you awake while in the middle of the dream, you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to fully recall and remember it, but what use is it when you wake up while in the middle of solving something. Mostly, you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to recall dreams which are vivid and interesting in content making you curious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah, this is my interpretation of dreams. If your dreams don&amp;rsquo;t scare you, they aren&amp;rsquo;t big enough, so dream big!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: Not taking anything away from EM Forster for he was one of the best science fiction writers in the world. Plus, this is just my view of a dream, you may not agree with this, but this is what I believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: This article was first published in my retired &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reasonwhyy.blogspot.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; on 17 November 2015. This is a copy of it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why life will be tough without a bean bag for me</title>
      <link>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/why-life-will-be-tough-without-a-bean-bag-for-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://aparajith21.github.io/post/why-life-will-be-tough-without-a-bean-bag-for-me/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;People may call me stupid as I prefer to live on a bean bag in this terribly hot, tropical climate of India and they may say that it&amp;rsquo;s bad for my health as it &amp;lsquo;traps&amp;rsquo; heat and makes the already hot climate hotter, but for me it is the most comfortable place to sit in, better than any other place I&amp;rsquo;ve sat on as it&amp;rsquo;s extremely flexible, I can change its position to suit me, it lets me sit in all kinds of awkward positions that are comfortable for me , and I think in the scientific point of view, it&amp;rsquo;s extremely comfy as it puts pressure on every single part of your back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t even use the dining table to eat, I use the bean bag for all purposes, whether it&amp;rsquo;s eating, watching TV or doing homework, there is not a place in the world I would rather be sitting on than the bean bag( except in places where the bean bag is there).
For all those who don&amp;rsquo;t know what a bean bag is, quoting Wikipedia &amp;ldquo;A bean bag (also beanbag) is a sealed bag containing dried beans, PVC pellets, expanded polystyrene, or expanded polypropylene with various applications.&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;d add the fact that it is the most comfortable thing to sit on!
For any person shopping for chairs, sofas, couches, trust me, I would rather buy a dozen bean bags and put them all over the house. You&amp;rsquo;ll understand my words only when you get yourself a bean bag and sit on it for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s only one little problem with getting used to sitting on a bean bag- it makes you lazy as hell and makes every other place you sit in uncomfortable. Even when you&amp;rsquo;re not sitting on it and doing something else, the laziness gets to you and you&amp;rsquo;ll feel like just going, sitting on your bean bag and relaxing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: This article was first published in my retired &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reasonwhyy.blogspot.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; on 09 June 2015. This is a copy of it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
